Guide to the James Ludovic Lindsay collection of French manuscripts, 1767-1863
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library Duke University Durham, N.C., USA
James Ludovic Lindsay collection of French manuscripts 1767-1863
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Crawford, James Ludovic Lindsay, Earl of, 1847-1913
1.75 Linear Feet 223 Items
James Ludovic Lindsay, 26th Earl of Crawford and 9th Earl of Balcarres, was a British astronomer, politician, and noted collector of books and manuscripts. Lindsay inherited a considerable library from his father, but during his lifetime he assembled the Bibliotheca Lindesiana, one of the largest private libraries of the nineteenth century. In the 1880s, Lindsay’s fortunes suffered and he was forced to sell much of his rare book library, although he continued to collect proclamations, broadsides, and manuscripts of the French Revolutionary era. After Lindsay’s death, his heirs auctioned off most of what remained of his collections, including his French manuscripts.
Collection consists of selected letters, administrative papers, and other manuscripts, chiefly of the French Revolutionary and Napoleonic periods, that bear the bookplate and previously formed part of the Bibliotheca Lindesiana, the private library of James Ludovic Lindsay, 26th Earl of Crawford. Lindsay's collection of French manuscripts was auctioned off by Sotheby's between 1924 and 1925 and a small portion was acquired by Duke in 1960. Duke's collection represents a very small fraction of Lindsay's original collection and consists chiefly of manuscripts, with typed transcripts in French, that document various aspects of civil administration including letters from the prefects of various departments, letters from government ministers, and several letters addressed to Comte Collin de Sussy, Minister of Commerce and Manufacturing, and the Comte d'Antraigues. Other materials in the collection include letters in English from French elites to British nobility, such as to the Duke of York, and letters from French aristocrats to government officials. Examples include a letter addressed to Napoleon Bonaparte from Arnoud Joubert, a lawyer at the imperial court of Paris, discussing the possibility of receiving a medal of honor, and a letter from Cardinal Albani to Alexander I, Emperor of Russia, requesting the Emperor's protection from French authorities. The collection also includes some manuscripts and engravings acquired separately that do not bear the Bibliotheca Lindesiana bookplate.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The James Ludovic Lindsay collection of French manuscripts were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a purchase in 1960.
Biographical Note
James Ludovic Lindsay, 26th Earl of Crawford and 9th Earl of Balcarres, was a British astronomer, politician, and noted collector of books and manuscripts. Lindsay inherited a considerable library from his father, but during his lifetime he assembled the Bibliotheca Lindesiana, one of the largest private libraries of the nineteenth century. In the 1880s, Lindsay’s fortunes suffered and he was forced to sell much of his rare book library, although he continued to collect proclamations, broadsides, and manuscripts of the French Revolutionary era. After Lindsay’s death, his heirs auctioned off most of what remained of his collections, including his French manuscripts.
Collection Overview
Collection consists of selected letters, administrative papers, and other manuscripts, chiefly of the French Revolutionary and Napoleonic periods, that bear the bookplate and previously formed part of the Bibliotheca Lindesiana, the private library of James Ludovic Lindsay, 26th Earl of Crawford. Lindsay's collection of French manuscripts was auctioned off by Sotheby's between 1924 and 1925 and a small portion was acquired by Duke in 1960. Duke's collection represents a very small fraction of Lindsay's original collection and consists chiefly of manuscripts, with typed transcripts in French, that document various aspects of civil administration including letters from the prefects of various departments, letters from government ministers, and several letters addressed to Comte Collin de Sussy, Minister of Commerce and Manufacturing, and the Comte d'Antraigues. Other materials in the collection include letters in English from French elites to British nobility, such as to the Duke of York, and letters from French aristocrats to government officials. Examples include a letter addressed to Napoleon Bonaparte from Arnoud Joubert, a lawyer at the imperial court of Paris, discussing the possibility of receiving a medal of honor, and a letter from Cardinal Albani to Alexander I, Emperor of Russia, requesting the Emperor's protection from French authorities. The collection also includes some manuscripts and engravings acquired separately that do not bear the Bibliotheca Lindesiana bookplate.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Alexander I, Emperor of Russia, 1777-1825
Alquier, Charles Jean-Marie, 1752-1826
Antraigues, Emmanuel-Henri-Louis Alexandre de Launay, comte d’, 1753-1812
Azéma, Michel, 1752-1827
Brissac, Augustin-Marie-Paul-Pétronille-Timoléon de Cossé, duc de, 1775-1848
Caprara, Giovanni Battista, 1733-1810
Chabot, Georges Antoine, 1758-1819
Chasset, Charles Antoine, 1745-1824
Chazaud, Jean-François-Simon, 1747-1818
Crawford, James Ludovic Lindsay, Earl of, 1847-1913
Dauchy, Luc-Jacques-Edouard, 1757-1817
Debry, Jean-Antoine-Joseph, 1760-1834
Decrès, Denis, duc, 1761-1820
Delaunay, Pierre-Marie, 1755-1814
Fleurieu, C. P. Claret (Charles Pierre Claret), comte de, 1738-1810
Fourcroy, Antoine-François de, comte, 1755-1809
François de Neufchâteau, Nicolas Louis, comte, 1750-1828
Gleizal, Claude, 1761-1833
Grégoire, Henri, 1750-1831
Guyton de Morveau, Louis-Bernard, 1737-1816
Hardy, Antoine-François, 1748-1823
Jaucourt, Arnail François, 1757-1852
Jourdan, Jean-Baptiste, 1762-1833
Julien, Jean, 1750-1828
Ladoucette, J. C. F. (Jean Charles François), baron de, 1772-1848
Leckie, Gould Francis
Lepelletier de Saint-Fargeau, Félix, 1769-1837
Lequinio, J. M. (Joseph Marie), 1755-1813
Loisel, Pierre, ca. 1750-1812
Mailhe, Jean-Baptiste, 1754-1834
Napoleon I, Emperor of the French, 1769-1821
Napoleon III, Emperor of the French, 1808-1873
Pellissier, Denis-Marie, 1765-1821
Quinette, Nicolas Marie, 1762-1821
Ramel de Nogaret, Dominique-Vincent, 1760-1829
Richard, Joseph-Etienne, 1761-1834
Roederer, P.-L. (Pierre-Louis), 1754-1835
Rousseau, Jean, 1738-1812
Rouyer, Jean Pascal, 1761-1819
Royou, Jacques-Corentin, 1745?-1828
Saurine, Jean-Pierre, 1733-1813
Sussy, Jean-Baptiste Collin, comte de, 1750-1826
Talleyrand-Périgord, Charles Maurice de, prince de Bénévent, 1754-1838
Tallien, Jean-Lambert, 1767-1820
Treilhard, M., (Jean-Baptiste), 1742-1810
Vansittart, George, 1745-1825
Villemanzy, Jacques-Pierre Orillard, comte de, 1751-1830
Walpole, Robert, 1736-1810
France -- History -- 1789-1815
France -- History -- 1789-1900
France -- History -- Revolution, 1789-1799
Contents of Collection
- Manuscripts with the Bibliotheca Lindesiana bookplate, 1792-1835, (4 boxes)
  Series includes manuscripts, chiefly of the French Revolutionary and Napoleonic period, collected by James Ludovic Lindsay, 26th Earl of Crawford. Manuscripts in this series bear the "Bibliotheca Lindesiana" bookplate and include typed transcripts (in French) prepared by librarians and scholars in Lindsay's employ.
  Arranged chronologically, with some exceptions.
  - Letter from Jeanne Lambert Tallien, 1792 Sept. 1 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Letter from Robert Walpole, 1794 Mar. 3 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Letter about a convention that was scheduled to occur.
  - Letter from Jeanne Mirabeau Lasteyrie Dussaillant to Barras, 1797 Sept. 6 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Letter informs Barras that someone wanted to meet him.
  - Letter from Joseph-Etienne Richard to Perregaux, 1801 Mar. 24 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Richard asks his banker Perregaux for a loan.
  - Letter from Bon Jacques Gabriel Bernardin Ribert to Vasselin, 1801 Oct. 20 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Ribert asks for a loan from Vasselin.
  - Letter from Pierre-Marie Delaunay to Villars, 1801 Dec. 1 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Delaunay asks Villars to help him meet Cambaceres.
  - Letter from Jean Baptiste Detcheverry, 1802 Jan. 16 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Detcheverry asks if his friend will receive his passport.
  - Letter from Count Henri Grégoire, 1802 Jan. 18 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Henri Grégoire mentions that Durand is giving him a memoire.
  - Letter from Louis Etienne Beffroy to Monsieur Choquet, 1802 Jan. 24 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Beffroy pays Mr. Choquet back.
  - Letter from Jean-François Simon Chazaud to Laquitanne, 1802 Mar. 7 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Chazaud writes to Laquintanne to let him know that Mr. Garrigou and Dupre cannot pay him back the sum Laquintanne had lent them because their activities had not benefited from the revolution.
  - Proof of receipt from Jean-Baptiste Mailhe, 1802 Mar. 15 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Mailhe states that he has received the payment owed him by Coste, Vidal and Viguer.
  - Letter from Jean Pascal Rouyer to Coste, 1802 Sept. 8 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Rouyer informs Coste that he will be waiting to meet with him the next day
  - Letter from Claude Gleizal, 1802 Nov. 27 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Gleizal, an attorney, attaches documents that show that Guishon worked for the Rochemaura square.
  - Letter from Mollevaut to the Minister of Finance, 1802 Dec. 20 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Mallevaut asks the minister for a job, arguing that both of his brothers died in service and therefore the government is indebted to him.
  - Letter from Louis-Bernard Guyton-Morveau to Chateau Giron, 1803 Jan. 7 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Guyton Morveau thanks Chateau-Giron for the Russian coins he gave him, and in exchange gives him newly minted coins.
  - Letter from P.A. Count Merlin de Douai, 1803 Feb. 8 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Merlin asks a government official for a duplicate of the decision of the judge against Claude Bassinet.
  - Letter from Denis-Marie Pellissier to Lucien Bonaparte Tribun, 1803 Mar. 15 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    Pellissier asks (begs) Tribun for his protection.
  - Letter from Jean Julien (de Toulouse) to Perregaux, 1803 Mar. 22 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    Julien informs Perregaux (banker) that his son will be in Paris and hopes they can meet. His son will be selling pieces of art, and he encourages Perregaux to take a look and perhaps buy something.
  - Letter from Delahaye to the Minister of Finance, 1803 Apr. 14 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    Delahaye asks the minister if he can be transferred to another region in France, preferably by the sea (where he is from) or bordering his region.
  - Letter from Georges Antoine Chabot to the French state advisor, 1803 Apr. 16 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    Chabot recommends Conny L'hopital who would work with the advisor.
  - Letter from Jean-Baptiste Jourdan to Regnier, 1803 May 19 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    Jourdan tries to persuade Regnier who to chose as 1st consulate.
  - Letter from Joseph Marie Lequinio Kerblay to the marine minister, 1803 Jul. 25 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    Lequinio states that he has attached the instructions that were written according to the treaty.
  - Letter from Jean Des Anciens Rousseau to Cretet, 1803 Oct. 6 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    Rousseau asks Cretet if he could hire Duc to work with him.
  - Letter from Charles Jean-Marie Alquier to Perregaux, 1803 Nov. 23 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    Alquier asks Perregaux to transfer money from his account in order to pay Mrs. De la Clos.
  - Letter from Charles Antoine Chasset (senator) to the prefect of the Ardennes, 1803 Dec. 9 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    Chasset asks the prefect to read over his letter, seal it and send it to another government official
  - Letter from Gilles Porcher (senator) to Saladin (secretary general of the High Justice Ministry), 1804 Jan. 6 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    Porcher recommends Locquin for the job that Saladin was advertising.
  - Letter from Charles Antoine Hourier Eloy to Dupenty, 1804 Feb. 20 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    Hourier Eloy congratulates Dupenty on the fact his son got accepted to a school in Rheims.
  - Letter from A. F. Fourcroy to the administration of the school of France, 1804 Mar. 2 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    Fourcroy names Pastoret as the law of nature and society professor in the place of Bouchaud who passed away.
  - Letter from Antoine-François Hardy to Gaudin, Finance Minister, 1804 Mar. 21 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    Hardy asks Gaudin for help to find a job, because since the revolution, he sees his funds have been decreasing.
  - Letter from Jean-Baptiste Joseph Delecloy to Regnier, Minister of Justice, 1804 Apr. 11 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    Delecloy sends a letter nominating himself.
  - Letter from Beauvais Benoit Lesterpt, 1804 May 11 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    Lesterpt explains a trial he has in Poitiers and asks the recipient to be his lawyer.
  - Letter from Michel Azéma to Mithie, Chief of the Ministry of Finance, 1804 May 15 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    Azéma asks Mithie to present a list of people for the minister and consulate.
  - Letter from the State Advisor to Molinos, 1805 Aug. 6 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    The advisor asks Molinos (architect) to send him the work plan.
  - Letter from Jaques-Corentin Royou, 1805 Nov. 11 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    Royau (Lawyer) sends a letter to city hall.
  - Letter from Ramel de Nogaret to Perregaux, 1805 Nov. 26 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    Ramel de Nogaret informs Perregaux (banker) that he has taken money from his account, and assures him that the payment will be on time.
  - Letter from Cardinal Joseph Albani to the Emperor of Russia, Alexander I, 1805 Dec. 31 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    Albani asks the emperor for his protection and offers his services
  - Letter from Jean Charles François Ladoucette, 1806 Feb. 25 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    The prefect Ladoucette sends a letter to the Director of Customs asking to get Dominique Fontaine's money back.
  - Letter from De Lattre to Dupuy, 1806 Feb. 26 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    De Lattre thanks Dupuy for the elegy that he has written for the death of his nephew.
  - Letter from Nicolas Maries Quinette to M. Jullien., 1806 Apr. 5 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    Quinette discusses M. Jullien's book on education
  - Letter from Charles Pierre Claret, Count De Fleurieu, 1806 May 9 (Box 1, Folder 40)
    Fleurieu thanks the person for the copy of his notes on his interesting journey and discusses the growth of a region in Russia
  - Letter from Alex (?) to the Minister of Finance, 1806 Sept. 5 (Box 1, Folder 41)
    Alex informs the minister that there has been a change, and a new individual will be starting work.
  - Letter from Jean-Antoine-Joseph Debry, 1806 Oct. 8 (Box 1, Folder 42)
    Debry sends a petition and asks the president of the petition committee to provide aid for an older citizen.
  - Letter from Philip Howard to d'Antraigues, 1806 Nov. 4 (Box 1, Folder 43)
    Howard writes to his friend and discusses his situation after the revolution
  - Letter from George Vansittart to d'Antraigues, 1806 Dec. 12 (Box 1, Folder 44)
    Vansittart writes for Lord Grenville and thanks the Count d'Antraigues for his service leaving Russia.
  - Letter from Cardinal Giovanni Battista Caprara, 1806 Dec. 16 (Box 1, Folder 45)
    In Latin.
  - Letter from Frochot, 1806 Dec. 31 (Box 1, Folder 46)
    Frochot asks that Mr. Lechart be appointed a referefaire in the court that has yet to be created for the Cour des Comptes.
  - Letter from Philip Howard to d'Antraigues, 1807 Feb. 10 (Box 1, Folder 47)
    Howard discusses his whereabouts and plans during his visit in and around London
  - Letter from Il Canonico Spoturno to Francesco Braccini (in Paris), 1807 Mar. 17 (Box 1, Folder 48)
    In Italian.
  - Letter from J. MacPherson to Count d'Antraigues, 1807 May 10 (Box 1, Folder 49)
    MacPherson discusses the protectors of Europe and a journey around Europe
  - Letter from J. MacPherson to Count d'Antragues, 1807 Jun. 18 (Box 1, Folder 50)
    MacPherson asks d'Antragues to write to him about his travel and the true hero of civilization (?)
  - Letter from O. Mackenzie to Count d'Antraigues, 1807 Aug. 17 (Box 1, Folder 51)
    Mackenzie informs the Count d'Antraigues that everything is ready for the attack.
  - Letter from Pierre Loisel to Sussy, 1807 Aug. 17 (Box 1, Folder 52)
    Loisel thanks Sussy for his decision to ban trade with countries that are at war with France.
  - Letter from Cardinal Jean-Baptiste de Belloy to Bourges, 1807 Nov. 8 (Box 1, Folder 53)
    Belloy informs Bourges that His Majesty has agreed to open a school, and that he must present himself on time to the location on the opening day.
  - Letter from Nicolas Harmand to the Minister of Finance, 1807 Dec. 13 (Box 1, Folder 54)
    Harmand asks the Minister to transfer Andre Moreau to another job.
  - Letter from Denis Decrès to the State Advisor, 1808 Mar. 14 (Box 2, Folder 55)
    Decrès writes to the State Advisor asking for him to lift the ban that has been placed on certain buildings.
  - Letter from the administrative prefect of Taro to the Minister of the Interior, 1808 Jun. 11 (Box 2, Folder 56)
    The prefect asks the Minister to give a sum of 100 francs to the five families whose fathers died in the terrible explosion at the mill.
  - Letter from Abbey of La Boissiere to Armand, 1808 Jul. 29 (Box 2, Folder 57)
    La Boissiere informs Armand that he is sending a trunk with books and informs him that he will continue to send him his brochures.
  - Letter from Philip Howard of Corby Castle to the Count d'Antraigues, 1808 Dec. 3 (Box 2, Folder 58)
    A friendly letter from Howard to d'Antraigues discussing his situation.
  - Letter from François de Neufchâteau to Sauvo, 1808 Dec. 31 (Box 2, Folder 59)
    Neufchâteau sends Sauvo a pamphlet.
  - Letter from J. Lagarde, prefect of La Seine et Marne, to Le Grand, 1809 Apr. 15 (Box 2, Folder 60)
    Lagarde asks Le Grand whether a rumor is true or not.
  - Letter from the Abbey Thibaudeau, prefect of Marseille, to another prefect, 1809 Oct. 22 (Box 2, Folder 61)
    Requests the prefect to take back an indemnity.
  - Letter from Thibaudeau, prefect of Marseille, 1809 Nov. 21 (Box 2, Folder 62)
  - Letter from Gould Francis Leckie to d'Antraigues, 1809 Dec. 31 (Box 2, Folder 63)
    Leckies discusses the meaning of a letter sent by Mr. Canning to the Count.
  - Envelope and seal addressed to the Count d'Antraigues, 1810 (Box 2, Folder 64)
  - Letter from Candras to Mr. Le Chevalier Monnay, 1810 Jan. 7 (Box 2, Folder 65)
    Candras discusses the letter he had received from Monnay on the 6th of the month.
  - Letter from Dauchy to Laugier, 1810 Jan. 11 (Box 2, Folder 66)
    Dauchy informs Laugier that he must be present at the Customs organization project.
  - Letter from Timoléon de Cossé, duc de Brissac, to Mrs. Bourbon Busses?, 1810 Feb. 24 (Box 2, Folder 67)
    Brissac discusses Mrs. de Ghilini.
  - Letter from Jean-Baptiste Treilhard to Bellait, 1810 Mar. 27 (Box 2, Folder 68)
    Treilhard thanks Bellait for the elegy he had sent.
  - Letter from J.P.O. Villmanzy to Barberot, 1810 Jul. 2 (Box 2, Folder 69)
    Villmanzy discusses the situation in their office (they have to let some people go).
  - Letter from Jean-Baptiste Treilhard to Count de la Cepede, 1810 Aug. 26 (Box 2, Folder 70)
    Treilhard sends a letter to Cepede informing him he mistakenly received a book that was destined for Cepede.
  - Letter from Cound De Bondy, 1810 Aug. 31 (Box 2, Folder 71)
    De Bondy invites the person to whom he is writing to his house in order to discuss the veterinary school in Lyon.
  - Letter from De Belleville to the General Inspector of Customs, 1810 Sept. 17 (Box 2, Folder 72)
    De Belleville thanks the Inspector for his advice.
  - Letter from Masson St. Amand to the Duc of Gaete, 1810 Sept. 19 (Box 2, Folder 73)
    St Amand asks Gaete to put forward his name as a candidate for prefect.
  - Letter from De Belleville to the General Inspector of Customs, 1810 Sept. 25 (Box 2, Folder 74)
    De Belleville reiterates a previous letter and discusses the orders he had sent and the situation of England.
  - Document stating an open loan from Freville, 1810 Oct. 23 (Box 2, Folder 75)
  - Letter from Jean-Pierre Saurine to a prefect, 1810 Oct. 31 (Box 2, Folder 76)
    Saurine informs the prefect of the transfers that are going to take place in the Haut-Rhin.
  - Letter from Langier to the "Count of the Empire", 1810 Nov. 14 (Box 2, Folder 77)
    Langier informs the Count that he has received his letter, and discusses a letter he received on the 27th of Sept.
  - Letter from Joseph Claverie to the Duke of Massa, 1810 Nov. 24 (Box 2, Folder 78)
    Claverie informs the duke that the slate of candidates for the tribunal was not complete. A certain Mr. Casebonne wanted to join the list, even though he lives farther away.
  - Letter from J. Reeves to the Count d'Antraigues, 1810 Dec. 12 (Box 2, Folder 79)
    Reeves informs the Count d'Antraigues that his friend Le Roy has arrived but that he has received instructions not to allow him to proceed.
  - Bordereau from B. De St. Andre, 1810 Dec. 17 (Box 2, Folder 80)
  - Letter from Lord Douglas and Clydesdale to the Count d'Antraigues, 1810 Dec. 31 (Box 2, Folder 81)
    Douglas and Clydesdale sends a letter to the Count to justify his negligence and answer the question the Count had asked.
  - Letter from Baron Lepeletier to the Minister of Finance, 1811 May 26 (Box 2, Folder 82)
    Lepeletier thanks the Minister for his letter and discusses who will take the place of Capitaine Sr. Regal.
  - Letter from Roederer to a Duke, 1811 May 30 (Box 2, Folder 83)
    Roederer informs the Duke that he has established the imperial court in Caen and that he believes that the first session went exactly as the laws regulate them.
  - Letter from Dominique Dufour De Pradt, 1811 May 30 (Box 2, Folder 84)
    De Pradt thanks the publishers for having published his article, and asks them if they could publish two more.
  - Letter from Spiridion Foresti to Commodore Rowly, 1811 Aug. 15 (Box 2, Folder 85)
    Foresti encloses a duplicate statement with all the necessary documents.
  - Letter from Jacques François Count Begouen to the Justice Minister, 1811 Sept. 20 (Box 2, Folder 86)
    Begouen writes a recommendation for Mr. Dorival.
  - Lettter from Henri Leonard Dreux-Breze, 1811 Nov. 5 (Box 2, Folder 87)
    Dreux-Breze recommends Mr. Suillant-Vachon to replace the recently decesased Mr. de la Barde.
  - Letter from Count François Maries d'Aboville to the Chancellor, 1811 Nov. 13 (Box 2, Folder 88)
    Count d'Aboville informs the Chancellor that he has received the letters.
  - Letter from Becquey-Beaupre, lawyer in the highest court of appeal, to a count, 1812 Jan. 17 (Box 2, Folder 89)
    Becquey-Beaupre shares the count's joy and informs him that Mr. Dupin will write to him.
  - Letter from F. (Ferdinando Conte di?) Marescalchi to the Count of Sussy, 1812 Jan. 19 (Box 2, Folder 90)
    Marescalchi congratulates Sussy for his nomination as Minister of Commerce and Manufacturing, and asks him if there is any place in his new cabinet for a Mr. Ferrand.